hello students we are going to look at
chapter 11 on alkenes
alkenes will be uh relatively different
from alkenes because for alkanes if you
remember it contain all single bonds
okay or cc single bonds or ch single
bonds and these bonds are relatively
strong which make them non-polar
so in order to force it to react you
need a very reactive species such as a
radical so
that's why for alkenes you learn about
free radical substitution towards the
end and
that probably remains as the major
reactions for alkanes you're going to
learn in h2 however for alkenes due to
the presence of the cc double bond
in the with the presence of a pi bond
which is relatively weak as compared to
the sigma bond
there will be a lot more reactions to
deal with and we are going to discuss
them i mean in a while time
so if you look at learning objective
11.1
sorry 11.3 e so there will be quite a
number of reactions that you need to be
familiar with
for alkenes so they are sort of listed
down here and you know that the name of
the reaction given is actually
electrophilic addition
and for 11.3 f you're supposed to
describe the reaction
of electrophilic addition in alkenes
and to be more specific you need to
illustrate the mechanism
okay and then um you're supposed to use
bromine as an example
but bromine is just a benchmark which
just you are required to learn for h2
but as you learn more you realize that
for assessment purposes and
to link up to some other topics
there will be
more kind of reagents that you need to
deal with
for electrophilic addition so bromine is
not the only reagent similar to deal
with okay uh 11.3 g is actually on
markovnikov's rule my colon course is
actually a russian chemist which worked
really really hard
in the past to
come up with some rules for
electrophilic addition and how when hx
is being added across asymmetrical
alkenes he gave rise to
different products yup so when he came
out with the rules back then uh he
didn't
he or rather he wasn't he isn't worried
he's not aware of the stability of
carbocations so
the rules
which he formulated
did not actually go into details
regarding reactivities yeah so
as of now we are aware that the
macronutrients rule why did he observe
the
hx being added in a certain way is
largely due to the fact
that the intermediate produce which is
the carbocarion
the more stable one we form and the less
table one will not be favored and
that explains why certain products are
favored yeah so later we're gonna touch
on them okay so uh without further ado
we're gonna go into the introduction so
uh we'll not spend too much time here
because basically alkenes any compounds
with a cc double bond you can
call it an alkene okay so
common alkenes will be
what you have in cholesterol because you
have a c double over here and beta
carotene is the orange pigment
present in carrots
okay so they are characterized by the
presence of c taubon it can be isolated
like that in cholesterol alpha-pinene or
athene or it could be conjugated okay so
conjugated uh
pi system is similar to what you observe
in beta carotene you can see that the
alkene here uh
there's a double bond single double
single double single double so the
alternating double single double bond
right is what we call a conjugated
system so uh it would be good if you can
understand what does this term
conjugated so basically for conjugated
system uh they are based they are just
separated by a sigma bond
um why is it called conjugated okay so
for a very simple reason i think we have
briefly discussed this in
the earlier chapter builder
one three diene right the reason why you
can get a conjugated system is because
if i have a unique alkene um over here
which have a pi overlap and i have
another alkene separated by a single
bond next to it
that is the possibility of the purple pi
system to be parallel with that of the
green pi system so when that happens
your
results or the system actually results
in a continuous overlap so this
continuous overlap we we say that the pi
system or the pi electron cloud is
delocalized
okay yeah
another way to describe such d localized
system
we can say that it is conjugated so
conjugated system generally means that
um when you i when you look into a
molecule you can identify alternate
alternating uh double single double
single bonds okay so that will uh help
you a little bit
and as to why they give rise to special
property etc
i'll leave it
i'll leave you to exploit on your own
as time goes by so let's not bother
ourselves with too much detail
okay similar to alkanes the nomenclature
will be relatively straightforward
except that you don't have a single
carbon member for obvious reasons
because minimally you need two carbon to
form a cc double bond okay so we begin
with ethene so
the starting prefix is still the same
which is f
followed by drops followed by cubes
okay
so uh i don't think
there's any uh huge differences except
that instead of uh ending with a and e
for alkenes it ends with b and e okay so
uh for three members we call it protein
and for four members we call it butane
okay
um the reason why for butane
you need a one over there right it's
really to indicate the present
the presence of the double bond okay
whether is it between carbon one common
two or carbon two and common three so
usually we number it um based on the
lower carbon membrane so in this case uh
if you look at this particular uh
butane right i number from left to right
one two
three four so the cc double bond is
between carbon one and two so we call it
builds one in
okay you can also quite one
view team
it is not a problem at all so uh some
textbook or website you come across uh
it may have
named it as one built in or two built-in
yeah but um
for the purpose of h2 we we tend to put
the numbering in between the prefix and
the functional group so we just quite
build one in okay so for build two in um
as the name implies it will be between
carbon two and three so if you have an
built in like this carbon one two three
four so the cc double bond will be
formed between carbon 2 and 3
and you realize from your earlier
chapter on isomerism that for build 2 it
is possible for it to exhibit cis trans
isomerism yeah because in our case here
the one i'm drawing actually takes on a
trance configuration yeah because the h
is opposite each other so for for build
two in you can have transmute two in or
you can have
cis build two in
okay so this is where the h is on the
same side
okay
and then um okay so the are you pack
naming i'll i'll just leave you to read
uh
a lot of details involved i i don't want
to go into details as you probably aware
that um i'm not
too keen
in discussing naming because when the
time comes then
i think the naming will be
uh will come quite naturally if you are
familiar with uh chemistry yeah but uh
maybe another thing i thought uh it's
worth mentioning is um maybe point
number four
uh if i have more than one double bond
present it is important to indicate not
only the position and also the number
double bond
yeah so double bond cc double bond as
you are aware is represented with in e
and e yeah so i'm just going to
highlight the in here okay so uh if you
have two double bond we'll call it die
in
three will be trying and four with tetra
in okay so uh maybe just to name this
okay why is it called five seven time
you thought after one three try in right
uh basically the main thing you need to
do maybe i should just uh
draw it out somewhere so that it's
actually easier for us to understand
what exactly is going on okay so i'm
going to draw it out using the skeletal
formula
okay so like this okay and then um
one up here and then
up okay
then down
so i'm going to number the carbon from
um
from left to right so
um it will be one okay in this case i'm
going to number it from right to left
because uh remember uh the main the
functional group here is actually alkene
yeah so uh they
if you if you want to indicate the
presence of the double bond it has to
start from the lowest numbering okay so
instead of left to right i'm gonna
number it from uh right to left so one
two three four five six
seven eight yep so in this case the
presence of the double bond is between
cover one two carbon three four and
carbon seven eight so we'll name them
uh based on the smallest number so in
this case would be one
three seven
okay oh sorry not one threesome one
three six over here yeah so that's why
you'll see this as one three six try in
okay and because there's a total of
eight carbon yeah so this compound is a
octa
triene so in this case we need to
indicate the presence of the double bond
so that would be octa one three six try
in
then after that we need to indicate the
presence
of the methyl group which is the
substituent so the methyl group is being
substituted in the fifth position and
the seventh position and that is why
it's being named as five seven dining
town
octa one three six try it yeah so uh
that's quite a mouthful but yeah that's
the way uh is being named so uh you can
just go through the list on your own and
then um it might be easier for you to
navigate around and then for uh
stereochemical descriptors such as this
and trans you will need it uh as and
when um there appears to be
a cc double bond where system trans can
exist so if there's only one um
potential position for cis and trans and
it's unambiguous we'll just call it uh
transist and then um trans uh
respectively but let's say there are
more than two position that is going to
get a little bit more complicated and uh
if you recall for your earlier in class
exercise normally we call it something
like cystis blah blah and then transist
cis trans and then trans trans something
like that yeah so uh i don't think um
i mean more complicated questions like
that will ever be given to you like
because remember the purpose of h2 is
not about naming but it's really about
you applying um what you learn in the
reactions and of course illustrating the
mechanism and how are you going to use
the basic reactions for structural
elucidation i think those are more
important purposes
for cycle alkenes they are being named
in a similar fashion except that
i think similar to what we have earlier
on we always start from the main alkene
functional group so in this case uh if
we were to number it we don't do it like
one two three four five six
uh because if we do it this way it will
it will be called 6-methylcyclohexene
and that sounds actually a little bit
weird so in that case we will number it
from one two three so we will call it
three methyl cyclohexane to make it
unambiguous
okay uh for this particular compound
cycle hexa1 for then again unambiguously
one two three four so the lowest number
will be one and four so we call uh this
particular compound
cyclohexa14
okay and this particular compound three
five dimethyl cyclopentene so again it's
the same um same thing we're going to do
so one two three so third position
there's a methyl group and then fifth
position that's another methyl group
so we'll call it three five dimensional
cyclope
okay yep
right so for exercise 1.1 we are going
to draw the structural formulae of
these two compounds so let's try to do
it okay so for
two three dimensional octa one three six
trine so again um the easiest way is to
look at the parents
okay so in this case the parent is
doctor so after means uh there are eight
carbon in total
and uh it's a try in which means there
must be
three
cc double bond okay so uh
i'm just going to draw a skeleton
structure out first so uh two oops sorry
it's just going to use the pen and then
okay so two three four five six seven
eight so to make things easy i'm gonna
number it one two three four five six
seven eight
okay and then um
at the first position
okay fourth position
and sixth position there will be a cc
double bond
and then a second position there's a
methyl group okay so second position
there's a midfield group i'm just gonna
throw it up third position there's also
another methyl group
okay yeah so uh this particular compound
in this case will be named as two three
dimethyl octa 146 trine uh of course
there is a chiral center so i'm aware
okay so there's a chiral center over
here and of course potentially uh four
five and uh six seven can form um
six trans isomers yeah so uh again when
we are doing the naming uh in this case
right we are not concerned uh with the
stereochemistry
yeah the reason why we are not
considering stereochemistry is because
uh
there is no indication in the naming uh
what should the stereochemistry of the
compound be yeah so uh we'll just draw
we just draw one of the stereoisomers i
think i think that would be fine and to
keep it unambiguous
okay and then for b uh
we're gonna have two ethal
three missiles cyclohexene
so again i'm going to uh highlight the
parents so the parents is actually
die in cyclohexane the dying is actually
at the 1 4 position so i'm going to draw
out
the seven member ring okay so some
member ring is drawn like this
okay
okay i'm just going to randomly number
it okay so i'm going to start from here
so one two three four five six
seven
okay and then i'm going to indicate the
presence of the double bond so that's
between carbon one and two
okay and then uh carbon four and five
okay like this and then
second carbon position i have an ethyl
group so i'm going to branch out with
the ethanol group like this
and then third carbon position i'm going
to have a methyl group so again you
might be aware that there is actually a
chiral center here so we are not
concerned with the stereochemical naming
at this point in time
okay yeah
another thing since i'm drawing the
cycle uh pain right i thought i i just
want to illustrate to you a simple way
of drawing
a
seven member ring maybe a six member
ring and a five member ring okay because
uh some of you might have a bit
difficulty given that this is the first
time you're looking at such thing i
think six-membered ring is quite easy
for most of you basically you're just
drawing a hexagon so to draw a hexagon
right uh i think
first we draw the rooftop which is what
we call the apex or the inverted v and
then we just draw the two lines down
okay
sorry it's not so easy to draw using the
screen okay so and then after that i'll
draw a v over here so this is a hexagon
okay or you can either draw it like that
or you can draw a rotate 6
30 degrees okay you can draw it like
this as well
if you if you feel like it yeah but
this will be more common but it really
depends on what you're looking at okay
yep then um
what about a pentagon okay so a pentagon
usually students do not have problem
drawing a pentagon so the you can keep
the top the same
and then for the bottom right you tilt
it a little bit to the to the right and
to the left so like this and then you
close up so that's a pentagon
okay so remember you tilt this part a
little bit to the left and this part a
little bit to the right and then uh you
will seal it off
with the two carbon
okay so um for a
seven membered ring right you actually
do the same
but you will exp you will tilt this a
bit to the left and this a bit to the
right okay so i'm going to illustrate to
you below so uh the top is the same so
here i will take a little bit to the
left a little bit to the right
and then for the bottom right what i'm
going to do is i'm going to draw it like
the
um hexagon but i'm not going to connect
them okay so i'll leave a little bit of
space to connect them using a straight
line
okay so it's like this yeah so this is
the way to draw a seven-membered ring
okay eight-membered ring i think most of
us know how to draw because uh it's
relatively straightforward it's actually
octagon
okay like this
yeah okay yeah so i'm going to move on
okay so the electronic structure for
ethene i think the main idea is the
presence of the cc double bond and i
think you heard me mentioning that the
weakest link is actually the pi system
because in this case the pi system will
uh will be the nearest and it's actually
on the surface of the molecule and uh
when if it were to react you will be the
first to
actually attack the electrophile or any
electron deficient sites for that matter
okay so uh because you learn about
hybridization right and if you heard me
earlier on in the isomerism lecture
there is an important need and there's a
real need for you to draw
an alkene
in a trigonal planar fashion yeah so
when you draw an alkene right
you have to make sure that
the
bond angle is 120 degrees so let's say
i'm drawing
cis build 2 in
so uh it has to be illustrated uh in
this particular manner
okay um of course we are not so strict
uh i think in most cases uh the strict
parts will only comes in uh when you are
asked to illustrate this trans isomerism
yeah other than that uh actually it
doesn't really matter but you'll notice
that whenever we draw it in zigzag right
it is already in the trigonal planar
geometry okay so for example like this
and that is also the reason why
uh skeletal structure is drawn in the
zigzag fashion because it's able to
showcase uh the geometry in a proper
manner
okay
and then um
of course you're aware that since trans
isomerism exists in alkene and well we
have discussed it uh quite extensively
yeah so uh in order for for for an
alkene to
to to move uh i mean to trans
uh to be transformed from cyst to the
trans isomer right there is a need for
the pi bond to be broken or to be
overcome uh it could
be overcome um through various means
like it could be either overcome by heat
which can be quite rare unless um
the system is heated to very high
temperature but sometimes heating alone
will actually cause it to undergo other
kinds of reactions so net so
normally heat itself is not the real
solution okay or you can actually
use
uv light okay allow it to undergo
electronic transition
uh
which is something going to learn in
university known as photochemistry
okay
or um you can simply maybe add in
momentarily and electrophile and then
remove it
okay which um i think we can um cover
along the way yeah i don't think we need
to discuss it right now yeah so once the
pi bond is being broken you notice that
the sigma is not broken okay so only the
pi bond is broken and there will be free
bond rotation
yeah because uh
remember that for alkanes or the c
single bonds um if it's a strict alkene
right it can undergo unobstructed uh
free bond rotation so the free bond
rotation will give you the flexibility
to to take on different conformation but
for an alkene it is not possible because
of the cc double bond so it will lock it
up in a certain configuration so in
order for you to
transform from cis to trans uh isomers
right there is a need to overcome the pi
bond and in order to overcome the pi
bond um something must happen which uh i
mentioned earlier on either um
you use uv light or you uh add a
reactant in to cause it to be overcome
momentarily and then a bone rotation
would take place okay via the cc single
point
yep
okay so uh says trans isomerism i think
uh we we have discussed in the isomerism
lecture we want uh we won't go into it
again yeah but uh remember that one
important condition is that um
uh the cc double bond right uh
do in order for you to exhibit this
trans isomerism uh the sp2 hybridized
carbon cannot have identical groups
yeah so in the case of two methyl
protein i have a ch3 over here yeah and
a h which is similar so even for uh
even if the other side let's say i have
a cl and then a br even though these two
are not similar right as long as one of
the sp2 hybridized carbons have the same
uh group then uh this trans isomerizer
will not be able to exist
yeah because uh there is no difference
between this particular um compound and
let's say uh
this particular compound
okay uh
it's a br
and then a cl yeah because i can
intercover them by just flipping into
the plane 180 degrees
okay
cycle alkene as we mentioned up to seven
carbon uh it only exists as a cis isomer
i think uh i kind of mentioned it uh in
the earlier lecture yeah uh for you to
have uh or for cis trans isomerization
to be possible
eight member ring and above is necessary
okay yeah so for exercise one point two
uh supposed to draw the cis trans isomer
of
this particular compound so
again
i'm going to draw it out so we have an h
here we have a carbon and then a cl
and then a double bond and then a ch3
and then a br okay you realize that the
four groups are all different
yeah so in our case here you
uh from what you have learned in h2
you are not able to name
these two compounds which means you
cannot name them as cis or trans because
cis or trans uh
here
means that
either the same group
usually is hydrogen on the same side or
they are on opposite side but in our
case here uh there is no difference
between the groups because they are all
different in that sense yeah but if you
move on to um let's say
you learn about h3 because h3 you learn
about easy convention then you are able
to differentiate between the two yeah so
uh just a little bit of extension if you
wish to know how to name them um
for the easy convention we uh
give
a priority okay to the different atoms
okay so in this case uh how do we uh
prioritize them we look at the atomic
number yeah so between h and cl
uh h has a smaller atomic number than cl
so in that case we will give we will
assign cl a higher priority and between
br and carbon
okay br has a larger atomic number so we
will assign br with a higher priority
yeah so the two higher priority groups
on the same site yeah for the easy
convention we call this z okay for the
other one we therefore it will be called
e because the higher priority groups are
on opposite sides yeah so you can view z
configuration as cis-like because the
so-called higher priority group are on
the same side but it is incorrect to
quite exist okay you probably will just
want to quite cis like but it's not cis
and this is trans like
okay yeah i hope that um explains it all
and another important thing i i need to
really really highlight to you is that
you need to draw them showing the 120
degrees bond angle which means um the
bond angle for sp2 hybridized carbon
okay it is of up most importance when
you want to showcase
cis trans isomerism
okay
okay next we're going to move on to
physical uh property yeah so similar to
alkenes
the physical property
is related to the strength of the
intermolecular forces of attraction
between the molecules so in this case
because they are all nonpolar yeah you
expect
dispersion forces to exist between the
molecules so you see that
the
uh boiling point and melting point uh
generally increases as i said generally
increases for boiling point but melting
point um doesn't quite follow certain
order for for melting like you realize
that builds one in actually melts at a
higher temperature as compared to pens
one in and then um
we're not going to discuss for simple
alkene but we're just going to
discuss it for
a slightly more complicated alkene okay
so that um hopefully you can understand
why yeah so we're gonna
deal with uh
cis1 two dichloroethylene versus trans
one two dichroity okay now you notice
that the boiling point for the cyst
isomer is higher
okay so it has a higher boiling point as
compared to the trans isomer okay
however for melting points is the
reverse the trans isomer actually has a
higher melting point compared to the
cyst
and then uh
you might be wondering what is the
reason because for melt for boiling
point right generally we
we follow the polarity okay so that
means that um
if
if there is a net dipole moment like
let's say for cis uh one two that
chlorine there is a net dipole moment we
would expect the
permanent dipole permanence dipole
interaction to be actually stronger as
compared to uh in the case of trans 12
dichloroethylene uh more of this persian
forces
yeah so uh because it has a net dipole
moment a stronger pvpd uh so you would
expect cs1 to that chlorine
require more energy to overcome the
stronger uh pvp so therefore it uh boils
at a higher temperature yeah uh but for
melting it's a it's a different thing
because for melting we are really
looking at um the packing okay what do
we really mean by packing
um so packing here so let's see if it's
actually your notes okay so it's not
really
over here i'm not sure if it's okay it's
not really over here but um so for
packing right we are actually looking at
how the molecule can pack in a solid
state
yeah so um
packing in the solid states here
actually means that if you can't really
pack very well
uh so for example the cis isomer right
because the cis isomer has sort of like
a inverted type shape
so um for inverted type shape um per
unit volume i don't think you can pack a
lot of it but for a trans analog
you can actually pack more but of course
all these are just you know uh pure pure
discussion and and uh without actually
further without actually proof uh it's
very difficult to be convinced but um
maybe all i can say is that if you if
you really look at
the solid state structure uh you will be
convinced that
the trans isomer actually packed a
little bit better than the cis isomer
yeah but i think over here um we do not
really have a diagram here to actually
showcase to you so uh i don't think we
we will
discuss more but uh i think for for at
least over here the boiling point will
be relatively straightforward okay so
for alkenes um
between the cysts and the trans isomer
you notice that the boiling point do not
differ by a lot because as
uh most of you are aware um
c centros isomer because alkanes are
relatively non-polar alkenes are
relatively non-polar
so
there will not be any noticeable
difference in the dipole moment okay
yeah
okay so yeah the melting point actually
comes next so we'll we'll look at
packing later so uh for exercise 2.1
you're supposed to
explain or just make choose an option
which also has the higher boiling point
okay so definitely
a and b are out because a and b are just
alkenes without a
without a polar um group
and then um between c and d
of course there's a net dipole moment
going in this direction so
i'll pick c
okay for the melting point um as we
mentioned earlier on
um the trans isomer uh
a little bit better because of the
highest symmetry and then uh the cis
isomer because being a type shape or
maybe a u-shaped uh kind of molecule it
doesn't pack as well
yeah so uh because
in a solid state right the
molecules are relatively immobile um due
to the fact that um very little heat is
present and they are
being put in
very regular intervals so in that sense
uh
if they are actually closer to each
other for example the trans and the log
or the trans isomer right if they are
closer to each other it actually allows
stronger dispersion forces to be formed
between the electron clouds
of the molecules so stronger dispersion
forces actually result in more energy
being required to overcome them yeah so
uh
in short when you are looking at boiling
point normally we are looking at
whether the molecule uh has a net dipole
moment okay so as to decide whether one
has a higher
melting sorry boiling point than the
other one for um
melting we are looking at
the packing okay whether is it efficient
or not so efficient uh again it seems to
be a little bit of a pseudoscience
because efficient or not efficient is
really difficult to see because it's all
i mean we really need to observe the
the packing in a solid state so it's
actually not very fair
uh to just uh make a blanket conclusion
that oh um
this molecule can pack better than the
other one but um what we have shown the
case to you over here is relatively well
understood and relatively simple system
yeah you notice that uh both the
um like for example for one two
uh
dichloro 18 um both the groups on bonded
to the sp2 hybridized carbon are the
same so it's actually easier for you to
to make a judgement call okay as
compared to let's say um
another another molecule where the
system translates might have different
groups yeah so in this case um
rest assured that i mean if assessment
question requires uh will give you a
little bit more data so that you are
able to answer it more convincingly
rather than
just blanket rule and say that oh you
know like usually the trans-isomer packs
better okay it may not always be the
case
okay
for solubility uh
uh as per
i mean what we learned earlier on right
um they are
relatively uh non-polar so usually they
will dissolve in polar solvents okay and
um for density being
um i mean being non-polar compounds and
being organic compounds uh usually they
are not as dense as uh
water so uh unless it's chlorinated
compound
okay so chlorinated uh alkanes tends to
be denser than water other than that
most
alkane alkenes etc they are usually less
dense than water because um at the
surface
or in the liquid state right their
intermolecular fossil attraction is not
as strong so
therefore in terms of density
uh they are not as uh
as as well packed or there's less
molecules per unit volume as compared to
that water so um you expect most liquid
alkenes okay etcetera to be less dense
than water okay so uh and because they
they do not dissolve in one another so
usually you see a very clear cut two
layers
okay then for
for viscosity so for viscosity of
alkenes usually increase with increasing
number of carbon atoms
present
because
the more
the
when there's an increase in carbon atoms
it actually leads to a stronger
dispersion of forces between molecules
so stronger dispersion forces here will
mean that um
they are more resistant to
free-flowing
okay so uh it's like honey i think i
always use this example like honey
versus water like because honey is
largely um carbohydrates with extensive
number oh h bonds so the hydrogen
bonding is relatively extensive so uh
because of that honey is very viscous
but water is not as viscous yeah so in
terms of viscosity you expect
alkenes with a larger number of
carbohydrates to be more viscous
okay next we're going to move into the
preparation for alkenes
for your batch we decided to take out
the contents for the preparation um
because we don't want to
repeat the contents again in the later
part of the topics yeah so you are going
to learn them um for
the elimination for h x from halogen
alkanes we're going to learn it in topic
um
under halogen derivative and
for dehydration for alcohols you're
going to learn it under topic 16 on
hydroxyl compounds yeah but i can just
uh very very um
you know in in a nutshell like to tell
you what exactly is going on
for the
preparation of alkene so you know that
uh
i mean later on in the next topic i mean
in the next section we're gonna learn um
the electrophilic addition of hx
onto alkenes so i'll just start off with
a very simple example on ethene okay so
for ethene right there's a cc double
bond
between the two carbon
and
if i'm
adding hbr
this is known as electrophilic uh
addition that's the name of the
mechanism
okay so uh okay so perhaps i represent
the hbr with a different color
okay so if i add hbr
i'm going to end up with
this particular compound which is what
we call a bromo alkane
okay so we're going to end up with a
bromo alkene so there's h here and
there's a br here
okay so this is the forward direction um
when
you subject ethyne to gaseous hbr
it is also possible for me to get
l-kin in this case ethen
from the
corresponding bromide alkene so bromide
alkane is part of the family of organic
compounds known as halogenoalkanes yeah
so that will be called the reverse
reaction yeah take note that this is not
at equilibrium huh
we are using different reagents yeah so
that's why i'm writing a full arrow here
so that so this actually represents one
reaction okay i can also do the reversed
uh in order for me to get the alkene
so the reverse reaction right is known
as d halo hydrogenation or otherwise
called elimination
okay so the reagents and conditions is
usually uh
uh we'll usually import ethanol lick uh
koh and will hit
under reflux okay so we'll use ethanolic
koh uh this might be quite mouthful but
um it doesn't really matter for now yeah
so uh one of the interesting interesting
thing about organic chemistry is that um
any reactions you can do forward uh it
is also possible to use a different sets
of reagents to effect the backward
reaction yeah so uh yeah so that is
usually how you should study organic
chemistry you should actually link our
direction in a huge reaction scheme
okay yeah uh it is also possible for for
you uh to get alcohol directly from
alkene so this reaction is known as
hydration yeah so in the process uh
i will not show you the reagents here
because you're gonna learn it later on
okay so i'm just going to draw out the
alcohol okay so uh
yeah you're gonna get the h
and the o h here yeah so for the reverse
reaction right um
it's known as dehydration because you
are removing water here so for the
dehydration condition uh usually you
employ concentrated
sulfuric acid heat yeah so concentrated
sulfate acid uh usually will
i mean concentrated software is water
loving so it will usually force the
reaction mixture to give up its of h2o
and
you might notice that um
dehydration is similar to elimination
which means it's similar to the
elimination of hx over here yeah so uh
to be more specific these two kind of
elimination is what we call beta
elimination
okay so you're going to learn all this
uh later on why is it called beta
elimination it's called beta elimination
because right it involves
the beta carbon the beta carbon is the
carbon next to the carbon bonded to the
br so this is alpha this is beta okay so
this is alpha this is beta so
in order for elimination of water or
elimination of hx to take place you need
to ensure that the beta
carbon contains a beta hydrogen
yeah so uh in short usually we call
these reactions beta elimination okay
now anyway uh please look forward to
learning them next year
it's going to be a lot more interesting
as compared to what you're learning now
okay i'm going to move on to the next
part on alkenes which is our focus uh
in this chapter
okay which involve the reactions of
alkanes
yeah so uh in a very simple
fashion i'm just going to introduce to
you what we call electrophilic addition
it's called electrophilic addition
because the
inorganic reagents
in this case usually is inorganic
which approaches the alkene right it's
usually what we call electrophile
yeah so
in this case
uh
an addition reaction um occurs because
the unsaturation is being removed
okay so that it's not going to lead to
any uh side products being released
okay yeah so uh the general mechanism
follows the uh
this particular fashion so there are
usually two steps
i mean i i use the word usually because
for simple electrophilic addition it's
two steps usually involve one fast i'm
sorry one slow and one fasted yeah the
slow step is usually the first step
which uh generates the carbocation the
reason why the first step tends to be
the stool step uh because the stability
of the alkene is being destructed yeah
it leads to the formation of a
carbocation which contains only six
electrons along it so it's a highly
unstable intermediate yeah the next step
which is step two is usually the first
step because the unstable carbocation
right uh
will be attracted uh towards the
nucleophile which is negatively charged
and it
is attracted due to um
attraction between opposite charges yeah
and such reaction is usually barriers
yeah so the next step is usually the
fastest okay so uh that's the generic
mechanism for electrophilic addition but
um
uh do take note that
your electrophile need not be positively
charged in the beginning
yeah i don't want
you all to have the impression that
electrophore must be positively charged
at the beginning uh it may not be okay
it could be a molecule with an electron
deficient site so for example hbr
is electron deficient at the hydrogen
okay due to the polarity difference
between h and br yeah so we caught we
will call hitch the electron deficient
carbon sorry the electron deficient
hydrogen or or you can call it the
electrophilic hydrogen yeah but in
general we call hbr the electro form
okay the carbocation intermediate is
formed um in the first step or in a slow
step of electrophilic addition yeah so
uh in general carbocation looks like
this so uh it has a positive charge
center at the carbon
uh bonded to three different groups
and
uh there's only six electrons around the
central uh electron deficient carbon
yeah so that makes it uh highly reactive
and it's usually trigonal planar in
geometry
in most cases okay i said usually
but i think for h2 wise it's almost
always all the time
okay
trigonal planar geometry uh give it some
interesting perspective because uh
if the nucleophile is present
nearby it will be able to approach it
from either either either side of the
train so if you look at the trigonal
plane um
in this fashion it's planar right so uh
we have the top face or the top plane
and the bottom plane
yeah so the
electron rich
nucleophile can approach the top and the
bottom plane with near equal probability
yeah so if all your three groups are
different you're going to end up with a
resonate mixture
okay so that is also an important
characteristic
of electrophilic addition
okay um
stability of carbocation is relatively
similar to that of a reticle yeah so in
general i think we mentioned earlier on
the lq groups tends to be electron
donating
yeah so the more alkyl groups the
carbocation is being bonded to the more
stable you'll be okay so in this case uh
i think the stability of carbocation
needs no introduction from left to right
less stable to the most stable because
for a tertiary carbocation it is bonded
to three alkyl groups as compared to the
rest with two or less uh lq groups
so in this case the carbocation center
will be
slightly more stabilized as compared to
the rest
yeah uh remember that stability is a
relative term so it doesn't mean that
the tertiary carbocation being more
stable means that it will exist for a
very very long time yeah it doesn't mean
that we so it just means that it will
tend to be formed because the activation
barrier leading to its formation is
lower
yeah so um yeah i mean i think what we
are teaching over here is
in a in a slightly more generic way
uh there will be a lot of details which
you if you really want to understand you
really need to read beyond what you are
given the notes yeah so i really
encourage uh all of you to to go and
read um on some of the text
on the text i uploaded um on you know
google classroom or you can just look
for information online i think that will
help a lot
okay um what else should i mention okay
so electron donating group stabilizes
carbocation
uh so
the more electron donating groups you
have the more stable will the
carbocation be and then um the
activation barrier leading to its
formation will be lower
yeah and there is a shortcut way of
representing carbocation
in in in the sense of primary secondary
tertiary so primary we can write it as
one degree secondary two degrees thirsty
three degrees however please take note
that this should never be pronounced as
it is that meaning you shouldn't
pronounce primary carbocation as one
degree okay you will just make you look
silly okay so uh it should be pronounced
as primary secondary and tertiary
okay yeah um maybe it is also worth
mentioning that uh not only will
electron donating group stabilizers
carbocation uh if i have a pi system
next to it so for example um let's say i
look at this particular carbocation
okay so this particular carbocation
based on our definition here is actually
primary why is it primary because this
uh the h right at the end i mean the
carbon right the end is bonded to two
h's okay however this primary
carbocation is exceptionally uh stable
yeah in terms of stability it could be
as stable as a tertiary carbocation if
not even more stable than the tertiary
carbocation why is that the case okay
because
if you look at this particular primary
carbocation right it is conjugated to a
cc double bond so if you look at the cc
double next to it it contains a pi
system
okay and then this particular carbon
over here right
has an mpp orbital
okay mdp orbital um
with a positive charge
so because they are all parallel you
expect delocalization
okay to take place or
or rather not take place like you you
realize that delocalization uh could
occur uh
for such a carbocation that is
conjugated with a cc double bond or with
a pi system so uh a pi system can be cc
double bond or it could be a benzene
ring
yeah it really depends yeah so do take
note that
the stability of carbocation is not
simply restricted to primary secondary
tertiary
or number of responders but you should
also take notice of the
potential stabilization which could
have taken place when it's next to a pi
system
okay yeah so for the electrophilic
addition of
hx
um we are looking at a generic hcl hbr
or hi usually we don't look at hf
again
similar to the earlier topic on alkenes
hf has some
exceptional
kind of reactions and stabilities we are
going to talk about uh i mean we're not
going to talk about h2 but um
if you if you are really interested in
you can read more about it but in order
to add fluorine you you you can't use hf
yeah it doesn't it doesn't work in a
normal way because uh number one the hf
bond is relatively strong okay it's like
562 kilojoules per mole as compared to
the rest of the hydrogen halites
okay so normally when you put hx we are
really talking about hcl and hbr
in fact even for hi
the ci bond being relatively weak uh
its occurrence again um
i mean when it's when the corresponding
outer compound form it might not be uh
stable enough for you to isolate it
really depends okay so
generally hcl and hbr are the one that
we are dealing with but of course for
the purpose of uh covering the
curriculum hi will be okay as well
okay so the general mechanism begins
with
the pi
system attacking the electron deficient
hydrogen uh which leads to the
heterolytic cleavage of the hbr bond
okay so you realize that
when the arrows are being drawn right
it's a full arrow remember i mentioned
that for alkane it is probably the only
time you're drawing a half arrow or
facial arrow okay for
other reactions we are we record these
reaction polar reactions
so usually involve
the pi bonds being electron rich uh
attacking an electron deficient uh
hydrogen and we must draw with a full
arrow head so this is a full arrow head
and then it leads to the heterolytic
breakage of the hbr and then we need to
draw it towards the
um electronegative br
okay so remember that when you draw your
arrow you draw it towards the hitch okay
and when the ball is broken it's drawn
towards the br because the lone pairs of
electrons is being formed
okay of course here we need to take note
that uh hbr alone the br already have
three uh
uh lone pairs of electrons so uh this
particular h
x or hbr bond the sigma bond is broken
the new lone pair electrons will be
being given over here okay and then it
leads to the formation of a carbocation
the first step is the rate determining
that as we mentioned because
uh it involved the formation of a
unstable carbocarion yeah because
on their own they will rather exist uh
individually
okay yep and then i'm going to move on
to the next part then the next step is a
fast step which involves the bromide
nucleophile attacking the electron
diffusion carbocarion and remember that
when you draw an arrow you must point at
the carbon and not point at a charge
so if you draw it
this way you'll be marked it you'll be
marked wrong
okay so this is incorrect
okay you must point at the carbon
because you are forming a bond between
br and the carbon okay so remember this
okay
and uh maybe for assessment purposes
i should also mention that whenever you
are asked to
uh draw the mechanism
or illustrates
the mechanism or propose the mechanism
yeah if you see all these command words
right you are simply required to just
draw step one
and step two there isn't a need for you
to describe everything else okay so
remember this there isn't if i describe
everything else
okay so uh that's why if you are
very strong um in understanding reaction
mechanism uh usually you can answer
an exam question relatively fast because
drawing mechanism
is really in your dna okay yeah so
remember this don't need to explain all
the words
unless of course there are some novel
mechanisms where
if it's ever been asked in h2
you'll ask you to draw the mechanism and
then maybe uh uh briefly explain maybe
one of your steps yeah i mean it
happened before so remember to read the
question carefully yeah other than that
uh usually when they ask you to
illustrate draw propose suggest
mechanism usually uh
drawing itself is sufficient okay and it
is also important for you to take note
that there is a need for you to indicate
the slow
and the fast step okay in your drawing
okay so remember to indicate the slow
and the faster
yeah okay
for the energy profile that again
remember earlier on i mentioned that uh
why is it that the first step is low
right because it leads to the generation
of uh
unstable
carbocation okay and that is why the
relative energy between the carbocariot
and your starting material okay the
carbocation is of a much higher energy
okay and then in the cross direction it
goes through what we call a transition
state so
this portion
is what we call a
transition state
okay it is also worth mentioning here
that uh in case uh you didn't um
remember what you learned in secondary
school a transition stage right is
different from an intermediate
okay i need you all to remember this
transition states are transient species
which occurs uh
say less than
10 to the power minus 15 seconds
and this actually
leads on to a new aerial chemistry known
as femtochemistry because femtoseconds
is 10 minus 15 seconds okay intermediate
usually can exist uh in a timeframe
between 10 to the power minus 6 to 10 to
the power minus 8 seconds so
intermediates can be studied and can be
detected uh
in the course of a reaction but
transitions they cannot so usually uh
okay so the major difference between
transitions they are intermediate
i mean in addition to
their period of existence right is also
the fact that um
intermediate already have
all the necessary bonds being broken and
being formed um
occurring so that means that an
intermediate itself uh is really a
speech species which you can so-called
isolate and maybe study if it's stable
enough but transition states usually
contains
okay let me mention usually uh
partial
bond
breaking
and forming
okay so uh how do you represent partial
bond breaking and forming maybe i can uh
i can just illustrate one over here so
uh maybe just let me erase this practice
okay so let's say we call um
okay so i'll illustrate it here so these
are just some additional information you
might want to take note of i mean for
for for academic uh for or rather for
full understanding okay so i call this
ps1 so this the first transition state
and then i call this ts2
okay the first transition state right
okay as i said are partial uh bond
broken and partial bond forming right
yeah so uh
at least the formation of a carbocation
right so uh you would expect the first
transition states okay so maybe i should
draw on the left
the first transition state will look
something like this
okay with a
and then a dot dot dot line okay so that
shows you that the
um
pi bond is being partially broken
okay and then i need to draw another dot
dot dot line
to show that the
sigma bond between h and carbon is being
partially formed and then another dot
dot dot line between h and vr to show
that the sigma bond between h and br is
partially being
broken
okay so usually transition state is
represented with a square bracket with a
double dagger so this is not this unique
sign right it's called a double dagger
okay so that might be something that uh
you want to take note of
okay and then um so this is uh ts1
and then for ts2
it will look like this okay so uh again
a big square bracket so for h
carbon h and an h here and then a c and
then an h and a h right so again we have
a dot dot dot dot line so dot dot dot
dot dot and then br
so it's a b r uh negative charge
approaching the transient states so you
can draw minus in a plastic if you wish
to but actually it doesn't really matter
yeah so it shows the formation
of the br carbon bond
okay some of you might be wondering um
does it matter regarding the length of
these partial bonds answer is yes
absolutely but obviously in this case
i'm not going to show you the difference
because it's not important
for the case of h2 in fact the drawing
or transition state for h2 right is only
important for one of the chapter which
is chapter 13 on halogen derivative okay
and we will deal with that later on
okay so we have the next um
exercise 4.1
okay so uh it was being asked hydrogen
bromide rex with 18 to form bromo ethane
what is the best description of the
organic
intermediate in this particular reaction
okay so let's look at the top your
organic intermediate is the one i'm
going to highlight in yellow so this is
the organic intermediate remember i
mentioned earlier on the organic
intermediate is actually electron
deficient at a carbocation
and any electron deficient sites what do
we call them we call them an
electrophile right
okay
right this is the electron it cannot be
a free radical because there's no
unpaired electrons
uh it doesn't contain carbon hydrogen
bromine because the bro might have yet
to attack the electron division carbon
and there's no negative charge because
the carbocation is positively charged
okay so uh the the only answer here you
can give will be c
and then there's also one thing that i
thought is worth mentioning but i hope
that by mentioning that it doesn't uh
confuse you guys
that is um of what we call a role
reversal
okay now you'll notice that uh okay so
in the electrophilic addition of hbr on
alkene right so i'm just going to go up
here right
you'll notice that the electron rich
site is actually the pi bond so we will
call the alkene a nuclear form
okay
and then of course we'll call hbr the
electrophile
okay now you'll notice that when the
carbocation is being formed right
originally the alkene is the nucleophile
right now it becomes the electrophile
and then the hbr now the bromide becomes
the nuclear form
okay so that is what i meant by role
reversal yeah so it is true that
you are not going to be an electrophore
for the rest of your life or not gonna
be uh and a nucleophile for the rest of
your life it really depends
at that stage in the stage of the
reaction what exactly is happening
okay yeah so we're gonna move on to the
addition to an unsymmetrical or
asymmetrical alkenes okay now earlier on
you'll notice that in our examples right
the alkenes are perfectly symmetrical so
meaning that
regardless of whether the h is being
added to the first carbon or the second
carbon it doesn't really matter but what
if it's an asymmetrical alkene what is
going to happen yeah so uh it will lead
on to what we call a major
and a minor product
and then um traditionally uh this will
be called what we call the markovnikov's
ruler but now because we already know
what exactly is happening we can explain
to you why
okay now you'll notice that um
i'm going to highlight this particular
hydrogen here with yellow okay so now
when the hydrogen is being added to the
first carbon
okay uh it forms a primary carbocation
if the hydrogen is being added to the
second carbon you actually produces a
secondary carbocation and as we learned
earlier on right the secondary
carbocation is actually more stable so
the activation the activation barrier
right
leading to the secondary carbocation
should be lower okay so in that case uh
it will be formed in preference to the
primary carbocation and because it's
falling preference
uh more of it will be formed and then
the bromide will then undergo a
nucleophilic attack on the secondary
carbocation to give you the final
product so two promo propane will end up
as the major product okay so one bro one
promo program will end up as a minor
product
yeah so that is probably something uh
which you might be interested in
okay uh as you as you as you study
okay yeah and then uh
i'm not very keen in talking about my
current course rule because my current
course rule as i always share with
students is like a no concept rule
yeah but if you want to you can
basically they are just saying that if
you are adding to asymmetrical alkene
the h is usually added to the carbon
with a greater number h
yeah and if you realize
in this case if it's being added to a
carbon with a greater number of h you
end up with a more stable carbocation
and that's the reason why yeah is being
added in that particular way
so in shorts you don't really need to
know my conicals rule in order to
predict the products
yeah you can simply predict the product
based on the stability of the
carbocation form
so i don't want
you to be stressed
uh in trying to memorize so many rules
because in fact there isn't a need to
you simply just need to be able to
predict which is the more stable uh
carbocation being formed and that's
about it and you are almost done for
alkenes
okay
uh i think uh there's a whole bit over
here to explain to you why yeah so uh i
think um i i will not spend too much
time here but basically the more stable
carbocation uh will be formed because
there's more electron donating group to
stabilize it yeah so uh because of that
uh the activation barrier leading to its
formation is lower i think i mentioned
all this early on okay then um with this
uh again we have another asymmetric
alkene here
so uh this is actually more stable
because it's a tertiary carbocation this
is less stable so uh it's a secondary
carbocation we
we will not say that it will not be
formed okay we are just saying that you
know the amount of it being formed is uh
much lesser as compared to the more uh
substituted or competitive tertiary
carbocation for that matter so therefore
this will be the major product
okay yup
so um for exercise 4.2 we are just going
to predict the major product in fact
i think the answer will be quite similar
yeah okay to the above okay so uh if you
are drawing the mechanism you know that
um
if my hbr is like this
okay
and then um
i'm going to have a polarity difference
with a pi bond attacks h
and then bridge towards the br
lightly that i'm going to end up with a
carbocation here which is a tertiary
carbocation and then uh so the first
step is actually the slow step
so this is a slow step
okay and then for the first step i
expect the bromide
okay undergoing a nucleophilic attack on
the electron diffusion uh carbocation
carbon and then uh in the process i will
generate this tertiary bromide alkene
okay yeah so i think that's about it i
think it's pretty similar to the one
actually in fact it's the same as the
one above
okay yeah if you are asked to draw the
minor products then uh you should be
drawing this so in general
if you're not asked to draw the
minor products
you can simply just illustrate the
mechanism leading to the major products
okay
now um i think earlier on i have
sky i'll give you a a preamble in that
um a trigger carbocation is actually
trigonal planar in geometry yeah so uh
if we have an alkene here
we are going to generate what we call a
trigonal planar carbo cation with
three unique groups ch3 ch2 63 and h
yeah so these three unique groups right
allow
the bromides
okay
i mean it's not allowed but uh these
three unique groups will result in the
fact that um i will end up with an
enantiomeric pair because the bromide
can approach the carbocation carbon from
the top and bottom plate with near equal
probability
yeah and uh how do i know that there are
an inertial merit pair basically i can
draw a mirror plane here and then um you
can sort of tell that this is like a
middle of this
and there's a test yeah so they are uh
inertial repair
you'll be
i think one immediate question you'll be
asking is what if these two groups are
the same yeah so if these two groups are
the same
i will not end up with a compound with a
chirocarbon so in that case it doesn't
matter whether it approached from the
top or bottom plane because i will still
end up with the same compound yeah so no
doubt that if the two rules are the same
and the
bromide will still approach it from the
top and bottom plane with near equal
probability but i will not end up
getting arrested make mixture because to
begin with there is no chirocarbon
okay so i think you have to be really
careful whether your final
product
contains a carbocarbon or not
okay
now um what about electrophilic addition
of halogens okay so electrophilic uh
addition of halogen pretty much follows
similar mechanism to that of hbr or hcl
okay but
in our case here i think um we need to
make mention that usually we are simply
dealing with uh chlorine
or bromine or in that case chlorine and
bromine dissolve in ccl form yeah we do
not
normally allow alkenes to react with
fluorine because it's simply too
reactive or even with iodine because
it's
not reactive at all
okay so in order for alkenes to react
with iodine
we need to
use other forms of
compound in order to generate the
electrophile
okay yeah then uh yeah so the mechanism
follow the same fashion so um
then you'll be wondering i think one
immediate question you might have is why
is there a delta plus in the data minus
here okay so the delta plus and delta
minus is due to the polarization of the
bromine electro electron clock when it
approaches the pi electron clock of
alkene yeah so when the pi electron
cloud approaches the
uh
bromine it will polarize it in such a
way as to
temporarily generate a delta plus over
here in the delta minus and this delta
plus being generated right will results
in electrophilic addition to occur okay
so again it will generate this
carbocarion and then uh similarly
the faster involve the bromide
approaching from the carbocation carbon
uh in the fast step
okay
some of you might
might read it uh might you might read a
little bit more okay um i mean it's
worth mentioning
uh
a lot of
research has been done on electrophilic
addition because all these are very old
chemistry they are usually being done in
the 40s 50 in the 1940s 50s and 60s
right
they actually realized that in the
electrophilic addition of
bromine
it undergoes
true i mean it
undergoes the direction
uh undergoes via an intermediate which
is
uniquely looking it's known as a cyclic
bromonium
yeah so uh this is something that we are
probably not going to go through in h2
but i think it's
worth mentioning
yeah so this particular cyclic bromonium
uh intermediate um
is able to lock the stable chemistry uh
such that um when the bromide approaches
it you will approach it from the
opposite side yeah so that is why uh
people actually notice that
electrophilic addition of uh halogen
right it's what we call a trans addition
rather than a cis addition
yeah so meaning that uh
when this is being locked right the
bromide
can only approach it from the
bottom yeah because uh so if i'm going
to sketch the 3d right so when it's
being locked it is sort of being locked
in this particular fashion
okay yeah so when it's being locked in
this particular fashion the only way for
me to break this bond right is that um
my bromide nucleophile must approach it
from the bottom so that this can break
some of you might be wondering how can i
approach my top cannot okay then i think
i will attempt to explain this maybe in
a tutorial rather than um intellectual
setting yeah so it can only approach
from the bottom
because um as you're going to learn in
your in the chapter 13 on halo
derivatives right this is some form of a
nucleophilic substitution reaction
similar to a nucleophilic substitution
so nucleophilic substitution usually
occurs from the rear of the c halogen
bond yeah so in this case um
this is the c halogen bond and uh this
this is the carbon and this is the rear
of the carbon so you must approach from
the back not the front
yeah as to the reason why i think we'll
deal with that when the time comes
okay
yeah so because of that
electrophilic addition of alkenes right
with
halogens usually result in what we call
a trans addition rather than this
edition okay yeah but uh this is not in
uh the curriculum so we will not attempt
to discuss too much on that yeah but do
take note that sometimes
um
for assessment uh
some clues can be given to you in the
context of the question based on the
preamble or the context of a question so
you need to
explain your answers based on the
context
okay so uh yeah i will not probably go
into more details i mean when the time
comes then um you you will deal with it
or when when you become a little bit
more familiar with chemistry then uh i
think some of these things will
will be something which you can accept
more readily
okay the next thing i'm going to discuss
is uh electrophilic addition of bromine
water yeah so in this case um
uh what exactly is bromine water so
basically is bromine dissolving in
water yeah so
as you might have seen the lab it's a
bit orange yellow in color
yeah so this is usually used as a
distinguishing test
for alkenes okay because when you add
blooming water you will usually
decolorized
and um the decolorization uh is usually
some sort of a test for unsaturation as
well
okay uh the mechanism
follows or what we what you learn on
under halogen so the first step or
rather slows that usually involves uh
the electrophilic addition of bromine
in this case the halogen and it will
lead to the formation of a carbocation
however when a carbocation is being
formed right some of you might be
wondering hey how come there's an oh h
where does the o-h come from right okay
the o-h actually comes from
water which is a competing nucleophile
because water also has lone pairs of
electrons on the oxygen yeah so in the
first step there will be two competing
nucleophiles water and bromides but
water being the solvent here right uh it
exists in much greater amount as
compared to bromides yeah so in this
case uh if you want to compare water and
bromide water will be because there are
more a lot more of it so uh yeah so
water will undergo a nucleophilic attack
onto the carbocarion and in this case
you will form the bromohydrin
okay you might be interested uh to know
the name of this compound because it's
actually uh quite important for you to
know the name okay this known as a bro
more
high drain
okay it's like a
hydrated bromo alkane something similar
something like that
okay
yeah
okay so they showcase to you the
mechanism over here yeah you might be
interested to know that um the fast step
it's not a simple step because
when the water molecule actually um uh
perform a nucleophilic attack on it
right um it is the whole water that
attacks and not o h minus
okay so when water molecules attacks it
um
in the fast array you'll notice that the
oxygen will
take on the positive charge
from the carbocation uh as to why the
oxygen takes a positive charge again
we'll discuss it maybe in a tutorial
setting or you can explore it a little
bit on your own but
as i said it might not be
very important for for you guys to to
pay
so much attention to it
yeah
and then later on um
the hitch
will
be deprotonated uh by either water or
bromide here and then it will lead to
the bromohydrin in this case bromo
ethanol being fought
okay
of course the bromide can attack but as
i said the concentration of water is
much greater so
the probability of water attacking is
much higher so remember that in chemical
reaction is always a probability game
so because it's a probability game right
when it exists in much greater amount
the chance of it uh
attacking
the electron deficient carbocation is
much greater
we have exercise 4.3 here so you are
asked to predict the product form when
proteins react with bromine water that
is contaminated so let me highlight this
interesting lines contaminated by
aqueous sodium chloride and they are
supposed to
explain why it is not possible to obtain
one two dichloro propane
okay
so
first of all right
i think we we are i hope we are on the
same page we should be able to
appreciate that um the first step must
involve the electrophilic addition of
bromine
okay
and
it can only involve bromine because
bromine is the electro fog so this is
the
slow step which is the first step
okay so remember that when you draw your
mechanism the pi bond attacks the
electron depiction br because it's being
polarized and then
um the brbl bond breaks heterolytically
okay and then of course i will draw the
more stable carbocation being formed so
this is the one i'm going to draw the br
is over here and then this is the
carbocation being formed okay and then
of course i will have a bromide
here okay so this is the first step
okay however right this particular bro
uh carbocation okay then there are three
potential nucleophiles present in the
system you notice i highlighted that
phrase contaminated with sodium chloride
okay so first of all right
it's the same as what we have above the
water will compete with it okay so water
will then compete
with um bromides and then water
molecules will attack
this
and then uh
in the process i will form um
the hydrated or rather the protonated uh
alcohol
okay and then of course this is the
first step and then the protonated
alcohol
will lose the h plus and then in the
process uh i will
i will be able to get
this particular oh this bromohydrin
sorry i mean i can't really write
very straight over here yeah okay sorry
this line is a bit difficult to draw
okay
and then um
the next potential products i will be
able to get involve the bromide
nucleophile okay this what we have over
here okay so attacking this particular
carbon okay so i'm going to get
one two dibromo
propane
okay
the next product i'm going to get uh
of course involves chloride because
sodium chloride contains excess chloride
right
so chloride will then
affect this carbon and then in the
process i'm going to get
bromochlorol
propane
okay so this is the bromo promo property
i'm going to get okay it's to be more
specific is one claw one bromo two
chloroplast
okay
and then the final part of the question
being asked is why is it not possible to
obtain one two dichloropropanes
okay so uh again remember what we said
earlier on
the only electrophile present is
thromine
okay there isn't chlorine electrophile
yeah so or there isn't uh
any source where i can generate either
cl plus or even a chlorine molecule so
without these two sources
i will not be able to insert the first
chlorine in yeah so that's why you will
never get one two dichloropropane
okay yep
and then uh if you recall what we said
earlier on under the the section three
right this is electrophilic addition of
water or steam uh to generate the
alcohol yeah so uh please remember the
condition because
generally students do not really
remember this condition very well
there are two methods of generating
alcohols from alkenes the first method
is what we call the industrial methods
which uses steam
and
phosphoric acid as the catalyst okay
however right you need to operate it
under high temperature and high pressure
okay
the next method is what we call the lab
method yeah you are required to know
both method really well because uh
sometimes uh you are asked to to use the
lab method instead yeah so for the lab
the laboratory method you are supposed
to incorporate coal concentrated sulfate
acid inside
okay and then after that um this is
followed by adding water
in the next step okay so the one and two
here right click notes they are not
added together
so it's one after
another
so uh the first step you need to
incorporate concentrated sulfuric acid
first
and then after that you use water to
either hydrolyze the intermediate wing
form or to replace
uh
whatever intermediate
group that actually attached to the
carbon in question to generate the
alcohol
okay so you are asked to refer to the
appendix format for the mechanism which
we probably deal with that a little bit
later on
okay so what alkenes would you start to
prepare the following
okay so uh i think um we can do that
relatively quickly so again i'm going to
count the carbon so i would have one two
three
four or five
okay so uh which alkene do you think i
will i will begin with um well i mean it
should be quite obvious because
to begin with carbon 2 must be the
carbocation i hope you agree with me on
that
so if carbon 2 is the carbocation so
potentially i can
have something like this
one two three four five
yeah i can have this particular terminal
alkene
where i add a hbr to it and then um
carbon five will gain the hydrogen and
then carbon two will be the carbocation
okay or i can have a double bond between
carbon two and three as well
okay so i can this particular cc double
bond between um carbon two and three
and then um so one two three four five
and then um when i subject uh this
particular alkene to hbr the hydrogen
will be added to the third carbon and in
in this way i will generate a tertiary
carbocation and then the bromide will
attack the tertiary
carbon
too
okay
or rather tertiary carbocation carbon 2.
yeah
for part b
should be relatively straightforward as
well
so again i'm going to do the same thing
so one two
three four five six okay so i'm going to
draw out the compound yeah
so let us try so in order for me to to
get this particular alkene i think uh
sorry to get this particular alcohol
maybe i can start off with something
like this
okay
of course um
uh take note that there are competing
products
yeah so if i'm going to
subject this particular compound to
steam right
potentially i can get other products as
well because
the oh can also
go into the other two carbon okay that
is possible or i can have a mixture
okay so uh yeah so this is uh one
potential starting material i can have
but bear in mind that uh in the process
uh i will not generate
this exclusively i will generate other
potential competing products
okay
some of you might be wondering um
whether it is possible for me to start
with let's say uh something like tesla
okay uh this is not ideal because if i
start off with this right you realize
that uh
in the electrophilic addition right i
will actually generate a carbocation
here
okay so let's say i already undergo
electrophilic addition here so
yeah so this carbocation all right we
will actually result in this particular
alcohol being predominantly formed
yeah because this is actually formed
from a tertiary carbocation yeah yeah
but for the earlier example right uh i
am only generating secondary carbocation
and because of that uh there is no
preference
yeah of course
there will be some preference depending
on
uh steroid hindrance but in general i
think the preference is very little so
um
and it's not selective so in that sense
i would rather um
leave things to chance yeah so that's
why um we propose something like this
yeah but if we propose the other alkene
which is the conjugated version then um
we're going to write the risk of getting
a lot of potential side products so
therefore it's
not entirely desirable
okay yeah
the next part is a reduction or what we
call catalytic reduction which uh uses
uh nickel catalyst
room temperature high
high pressure yeah so uh you would have
learned this
in secondary school or you would have
seen this in other reaction kinetics
yeah so um
for the for for this particular reaction
actually there are a lot of metals which
you can use like you can use palladium
you can use platinum you can use nickel
you can even use a rhodium routine but
take note that different metal may
require slightly different
conditions
yeah okay so
in general i think in our notes
we just give you a nickel
which takes place at room temperature
condition i think that one i think this
is easier to manage
okay yeah
there's a part for you to take note of
uh h2 with nickel catalyst is also able
to reduce other function groups yeah so
they so we'll discuss them in later
topics so just take note that this is
not exclusive to alkenes cc double
yup
okay the next portion is probably
another important portion and um
it's probably another uh subsection
which uh students
will find challenging uh it's called
oxidation okay
the mouth oxidation is not challenging
at all because
uh i think it might be quite obvious for
for most of our students so um for the
mouth oxidation right uh basically the
condition is potassium permanganate um
with
alkaline condition in this case uh
sodium hydroxide and take note that it
must be cold
okay and in this case i will form a dior
over here
okay so basic uh take note that this is
not electrophilic addition okay i i
think it's worth mentioning this this is
not electrophilic addition so um
oxidation condition uh
i mean no doubt the mechanism eventually
uh if you read beyond h2 curriculum
right may involve some form of
electrophilic addition uh but
in general we we don't want you guys to
learn it as electrophilic addition yeah
so uh in general you will call them
either mouth oxidation or
strong oxidation or what we call
oxidative cleavage
okay
and also take note that uh similar to
the earlier uh portion or earlier
chapters right we will balance the
equation using bracket o
okay we will not
do the redox balancing unless the
question requires you to do so
yeah so please remember this okay so in
general um when you're asked to write
the so-called balance equation
uh you do not need to incorporate
permanent as the species
okay yeah the observation is also worth
taking note of purple per magnet will
decolorize and you will get brown ppt of
mno2
yeah
this is as opposed to a strong oxidation
condition where the purple
permanently colorized
uh
to give a color solution which is mn 2
plus yeah so there is a slight
difference so
you might want to take note of the
difference in conditions as well
okay the next part is oxidative cleavage
uh
again worth mentioning because oxidative
cleavage is probably the most important
portion we're gonna mention
under alkenes
okay so for oxidative cleavage um it's a
little bit mechanical i would say uh in
in determining the products yeah so i
will go through it in in a little bit of
details but i think before that uh maybe
just let me highlight to you uh
what exactly uh
is going on or what exactly might happen
okay
so for oxidative cleavage right what is
most important for you to take note of
is the condition so you have chemilo4 as
well
but instead of alkaline condition you
use acetate condition
okay and instead of cold you use you
need to heat it
okay and
this actually colorized
uh it may lead to the effervescence or
co2 depending on whether co2 is a
by-product
okay depending on that uh if not then i
think the observation you want to make
will be the decolorization of purple
kml4
okay and in oxidative cleavage uh
how do we predict the products so that's
what we're going to go into next
okay
but uh okay so before we go into that i
might want to remind all of you that the
oxidation of alkene cannot be carried
out using potassium dichromate okay so
this is important cannot uh because a
lot of your seniors they get confused so
they thought that potassium dichromate
can do that as well so cannot only kml4
okay
some of you might also be interested in
the mechanism of oxidative cleavage but
take note that the mechanism is not
within h2 curriculum
and uh usually strong oxidation
condition for alkenes
uh is not a very well studied reaction
because uh it occurs too rapidly
and uh in most cases uh difficult to
study during that period of time okay
that is in the in the 40s and 50s
and in general because oxidative
cleavage generates uh too many side
products and it's not easily controlled
um so synthetically it is not a very
useful reaction
yeah so i need to emphasize that
oxidative cleavage uh probably only
is only important at the theoretical
level yeah because synthetically meaning
in order to make molecules
uh
we we will need to employ certain
reagents
in order to to do transformation from
molecule a to molecule b to c right
oxidative cleavage is two
i mean using kml4 is too strong uh
camouflage is too strong a reagent that
it's not synthetically useful
yeah so in that sense uh we are we are
really not too concerned over uh its
mechanism and that's why and that's also
probably the reason why it's not well
started um
even at the at the most advanced level
okay
yeah so now i'm going to go through a
few some of the important things
regarding oxidative cleavage and
hopefully you'll find them useful
because
the prediction of oxidative cleavage
products will remain as
maybe one of the
most challenging part um in your studies
of this particular topic yeah so perhaps
let me make mention um
to how to predict the products and then
uh it will help you in in this
particular journey
okay so the first thing i thought
okay so
you might want to uh be familiar with
this particular table
uh
but um
if you if you eat i mean
i mean it's it's
kind of a good summary but um i i just
thought that um
i could explain a little bit more later
on
okay so now
when oxidative cleavage occurs right
generally the cc double bond is being
cleaved okay so um
you'll be cliff cliff cliff
okay so remember the mechanism
is not important so we just need to know
that the cc double is being clipped yeah
which is uh
probably more important than anything
else
okay now um
again uh we are not we are not so
concerned over what exactly is the blue
box over here
okay we're not so concerned because uh
over here right we are mainly concerned
with uh what will result in the right
hand side yeah because if you are able
to predict what happened on the right
hand side right on the on the left hand
side is basically just another
combination of whatever
we have on the right yeah so you will be
able to predict the product
okay
so uh the first thing you want to do
right is
okay so let me just guide you through
you you
draw the same thing sorry you draw the
same molecule
okay uh
with the groups
okay so i will just draw the same thing
okay so i use the wrong word this it
should not be molecule the species okay
so this is this is the
um
the one i've highlighted is pink over
here okay i'm going to draw them
okay
and then
um
i'm going to replace
the double bond with a double one with a
double bond
oxygen okay so i'm just going to replace
it with a double bond o
okay double bond o
double bond o
and then we're going to ask
the first question you have to ask
yourself the first question
what kind of compound is this
okay so this is basically a ketone
okay so uh yeah so in this case you need
at this moment right you need to flip
back into your introductory organic chem
to understand the difference between a
ketone and an aldehyde yeah so a ketone
is where you have a carbonyl group and
then bonded to two r groups so we call
this a ketone
so
after you replace it with a double bond
o if it's still a ketone right
then you just draw this as a final
product yeah so this will be the final
product that you will draw
which is a ketone
okay
then um if it's not a ketone
it will be an aldehyde which is what we
have over here
yeah so this is an ld height
now
and ld heights remember that in
strong oxidation conditions such as the
presence of kml4 it will be further
oxidized to a
carboxylic acid okay why is that the
case okay i can kind of explain to you
that
because your ch bond
is the weakest link over here due to the
presence of the carbonyl oxygen yeah so
that means that your ch bond in this
case is sort of activated
towards oxidation condition yeah so
since it's being activated right so i
will not be drawing this
uh cage because it wouldn't deform so uh
you'll be further oxidized to a
carboxylic acid okay which is what i'm
going to draw over here yeah so you'll
be drawing a carboxylic acid
so the final product you're going to
draw is a carboxylic acid
okay yeah
and then after that you'll be wondering
uh how come terminal alkenes which is
the one with ch2 gives me a different uh
product well you need to look at this
particular compound this is actually a
special aldehyde known as formaldehydes
okay formaldehyde which contains
two activated ch bonds
okay so that means that these two ch
right
will be
further oxidized
to give me
carboxylic acids
and this particular carboxylic acid is
what we call
is actually present in your soft drinks
now it's what we call carbonic acid if
you remember we talked about it um
in the earlier chapter i think in redox
i think it should be redox yeah so
carbonic acid is actually not stable in
aqueous medium so it will quickly
uh
decompose to give you co2 and water
yeah so take note that carbonic acid is
not stable uh in aqueous medium so it
will very very rapidly decompose to give
you co2 and water and that is why you
get co2 as the side products oh sorry
byproduct
okay yeah so in short
to summarize what you should be doing
okay so first of all you
you cliff
and then you draw the part in blue okay
which i did earlier on and then you
replace the
cc double bond with a double one o
and then you ask yourself is this a
ketone if it's a ketone you keep it
okay
if not you'll be an aldehyde so an ldl
will be further oxidized to a carboxylic
acid
okay yeah but please take note that uh
oxidative cleavage does not always mean
that i'm going to get two separate
compounds okay so what i mean is if i
have a long alkene like this
and then another long alkene
okay if i undergo oxidative cleavage i'm
going to get two products
okay no problem
okay however right
if
it's a cyclic alkene
and i undergo oxidative cleavage
okay
my products will still be one whole
product which will be like this
okay yeah so uh it doesn't mean that
oxidative cleavage only give me one
product i can analyze two products sorry
only give me two products it's possible
for the nra one product if let's say
um
the oxidative cleavage occurs
um in the cc double bond within the ring
okay
there's also the special case of
oxidative cleavage where you only end up
with co2 uh
we probably don't want to call it a
special case but i mean if you if you
you wish to call it you can so normally
i don't want to um uh
make mention on the of this portion uh
separately because it's actually not so
crucial but i think um
maybe i should okay now
you'll notice that this particular
portion right
is pretty much the same as uh
this particular portion right so uh yeah
so you end up with co2 and h2o which we
discussed earlier on
okay
and then the parts in the middle
will actually give me
eternal acid or what we call oxalic acid
so oxalic acid is the
common name
so oxalic acid or ethanol acid
is actually
unstable
in the presence of oxidation conditions
so it will be further oxidized to give
you two co2 why is it unstable
i can roughly explain just very very
very briefly because
co is a very strong electron withdrawing
group okay so this electron withdrawing
group y actually leads to the weakening
of the
cc single bond here so this becomes a
weak cc single bond
so that a weak bond is usually
relatively reducing because uh the
electrons tend to be lost uh to strong
uh oxidizing condition or strong
austenitic agents yeah and chemical for
being a strong lazy agent is able to
grab hold of that electron very quickly
and in the process
yeah i'll generate co2 yeah and
therefore acid is oxidized from plus
three oxidation state two plus four
okay yeah so uh yeah you it might be
worth mentioning it might be worth
remembering the unique case if you want
to but if not then
it doesn't really matter because you
should be able to
work out on your own if you are if you
are
familiar with uh the chemistry of
eternal acid
okay yup so uh
what's the usefulness of oxidative
cleavage uh usually it's a useful tool
to establish the location of cc double
in a hydrocarbon or ring and then uh you
can actually use to distinguish between
uh
uh alkenes with
i mean i mean uh compounds with terminal
alkynes and those without because co2 is
usually uh being released yeah but of
course the first point is actually the
more important point which um you might
want to mention
but uh not to worry a question will not
be asked like that i mean we will not
ask you the usefulness of oxidative
cleavage usually
okay because uh this question again is
not so crucial
okay but uh oxidative cleavage is
usually important um
in structural illusion kind of questions
which you will encounter in your alkenes
tutorial
okay
yeah okay so uh yeah we're gonna have a
exercise 4.5 here so we are going to uh
try to draw the products okay so um so
there's some space here so i'm just
going to use all the space to to
illustrate i might need to erase s and
where necessary okay so uh this
particular alkene actually looks like
this so we have a l key here and then
like this
okay so i'm gonna
um
in addition to what i've taught you
earlier on right i think uh i'm going to
show you um
uh a very very uh unique but not unique
but a very uh systematic way of doing so
that um you will not miss out anything
uh that is numbering the carbon okay so
i'm gonna number the color one two three
uh four
five six
so there are six carbon in total okay so
the first thing i'm going to do is
oxidative glitch i'm going to cleave the
cc diabolic
okay so you realize that i'm going to
end up with this particular structure
okay so it's carbon one and two
and three so column one two three
remember what i did earlier on i'm
supposed to draw the double bond right
double one o
yeah
so this is a ketone right okay so if
it's a ketone we leave it as it is
okay because uh it will be the product
which uh we are going to draw
and then remember that carbon 6
essentially if you if you draw out it's
actually a terminal alkene
okay so there is a dominant ch2 here so
in that in that case for for carbon 6
i'm going to end up with a co2
okay and plus h2o
all right yeah
okay then
you might be wondering where do i get
the co2 and h2 okay so it's actually
here
so it's actually over here yeah so we're
gonna end up with co2 and h2o
okay so uh
this is the part we're talking about
okay and then um
moving on to the
moving on to the next parts okay
um
we're gonna have carbon four and five
right but um
you know above carbon fiber is what we
call the
interesting exception so remember yeah
so i'm just going to number this as
carbon four and five
okay so you're going to incorporate the
double bond o in
you're going to realize that you're
going to end up with a
ld height and then of course
acid right and remember that this is a
special case yeah so because it's a
special case right it will be further
oxidized so you feel co2 and h2o yeah so
i'm going to erase this whole thing
um
and then because it's co2 and h2o right
so i'm just going to redraw it a few
times so co2
uh carbon 5 co2 carbon 6 and then of
course the h2o
yeah so all together i'm going to end up
with three products a ketone in this
case a proper node
3 co2 and 2h2
okay yeah
okay so the next thing i'm going to do
is part b so again
same thing i'm going to number the
carbon now numbering carbon doesn't mean
i've numbered every single carbon all i
need to do is just to number the key
carbon so now cover one two three four
five six yeah so again for oxidative
cleavage i'm cleaving
uh
c1 c2 pi bond okay so i'm
going to end up with again uh if you
follow what i said to you earlier on you
can simply just draw this out
as it is
okay so this is the h and then a
double bond o and double bond o
so we just need to ask ourselves one
little question is this ld halo ketone
so this portion is ketone right yeah so
we'll just keep it as it is
and then uh
this portion is actually an ld height so
it will probably not survived under
strong oxidation condition so uh because
it will not survive it will be further
oxidized to give me carboxylic acid yeah
so you can draw this as the answer
another reason why numbering carbon is
good is because it helps you to keep
track of the number of carbon you are
drawing because sometimes students will
draw too many carbons usually one extra
carbon
yeah so there are six come in the ring
yeah so i did not draw extra carbon yeah
of course if you are the type of
students which wants your answer to be
very nice looking then you should be
drawing it straight chain like so two
three four five six seven yeah so i will
be drawing this as a straight chain
which looks like this so this is two
three four five uh six and then carbon
number one
so this will be the answer which i will
draw if i want um my structure to look
nice okay four five six seven eight
sorry not seven uh carbon number one
yeah
okay so i hope uh this uh numbering of
carbon really helps a lot and let me
emphasize that if you don't know what to
do number your carbon first yeah because
once you number the carbon um
uh the rest of the part is easy to be
accomplished
okay
yeah so i'm going to do the same thing
with a number the carbon one two three
four five six so again oxidative
cleavage i'm gonna cleave here and here
so yeah i'm gonna end up with two
portions over here
yeah so uh for those of you who are
already quick enough you know that
carbon number two has a h
carbon number six has a h carbon number
five has a h as well
yeah so um
without even going to further details uh
carbon number two will give me a
carboxylic acid and carbon number six
will result in the carboxylic acid as
well
okay and then for the top uh portion
carbon number five will result in a
carboxylic acid
and then carbon number three will be a
ketone
okay so if i'm just going to put in the
numbers this one two six and then five
four three
yeah you realize that it can be done
quite quickly if you are
uh
very sure about what's going on yeah if
you're not sure about what's going on
sometimes it's difficult um to actually
accomplish the task
okay yeah and then um with this
complicated looking molecule you know
sometimes um you realize that if if i
number the carbon it will take a long
time yeah well i mean
i think you should number yeah but of
course if you are able to maintain your
poise actually sometimes you do not
really need to number the carbon and you
already can
end up with the answers okay so um what
i can illustrate here would be i'm just
going to draw this out
in the way it should
and then double bond
okay and then um
double bond
oh wait sorry i thought i should draw
this out
separately
okay
like this
and then
like this and then
the double bond
okay and then the double bond and then
um
and then the
ketone here
and then a c c dot one okay so if you
recall what i did earlier on right
basically erasing actually helps a lot
so all i need to do is i erased
i erased i erased i erased and i erased
and then after that i'm just going to
replace them with a double bond o
double bond o
and then um
double bond o and then of course it's
ph okay double one o o h
double o o h
double bond o o h
okay and then a double bond o and o h
and then the final part is a co2
and that's it
okay so this will be the answer which
you're going to present oh i mean
presented an example of course it looks
ugly
yeah then if you if you are the type
that you know wants it to be neat so you
can draw it nicely like this is uh this
is proper known so i'm going to draw it
like this
and then this whole chunk is it looks
really really long but uh if you if you
look at it slowly so uh that's carbon
one two three four five six seven and
then eight nine okay so if i draw it
nicely it'll be one
two double bond o and then three four
double bond o and then five six seven
and then uh
eight will be
double bond o and then o h and then nine
will be double bond o and then oh
yeah so it can be drawn nicely if you
want to
okay and then uh for the other one will
be uh same thing one two three four five
six okay so again um
you'll be like this
like
this okay
and then uh like this
and then like this
yeah okay and then plus co2 yeah so this
will be the nicer version of the answers
if you wish to
but of course if you are running short
of time in exam just wack and then just
erase and then yeah just write it on i
think that will be fine
okay and then of course for planning
wise you need to
learn how to
write out the generic procedure for
distinguishing tests for alkenes
okay and then um usually for alkenes we
will use acidified potassium
permanganate which will actually result
in oxidative
cleavage
okay but you need to take note that um
the amount of acidified chemical for you
you are going to add right should be two
to three drops you shouldn't add too
much the reason is if you add too much
right then the kml4 becomes the excess
reagents
so the solution will not change color it
will remain as purple so
this is uh this is often a mistake which
students make during exams
i'll be doing practical exams yeah so we
are supposed to add one or two drops
make sure you add one or two drops not
too many drops
okay but usually we do not
recommend students to use potassium
permanganate as a distinguishing test
the reason is uh
potassium permanganate being a very
strong agent can undergo many other
forms of
oxidation which you
will learn later on so bromine water is
actually the top choice
but again bromine water add drop wise
not too many jobs
okay and then we have exercise 4.6
um
why should can we also be added drop
wise i think i've explained if you add
access solution will remain purple
because chemical becomes excess
reactants
yeah and you don't want that to happen
okay so drop wise is a must okay
actually same reasoning goes for uh
roaming water
okay then uh from bombing water if you
add too much in excess the solution will
remain as yellow orange you will not be
able to observe uh the decolorization
yeah and i hope you also remember that
in your practicals
please follow instructions carefully
when they ask you to add drop wise make
sure you add drop wise
all right
okay and then um
the summary of the reactions here i'll
leave it to you to fill in the boxes
okay so as to be
to familiarize yourself with the
necessary conditions in order to get uh
the elect
addition products
okay either the addition product or the
oxidative cleavage products for that
matter
okay and then uh
earlier on i mentioned that we have
appendix here uh showcasing to you the
electrophilic addition of water or steam
uh in the presence of concentrated
sulfuric acid
so
the first step usually involves uh the
electrophilic addition of h2so4
okay and then uh same same case
you generate a carbocarion
and then
your
hso four minus okay um
being a weak nucleophile will then
attack the electron deficient carbon and
you will generate this uh interesting
looking hydrogen sulfate species which
can be easily hydrolyzed in the presence
of either alcohols or
water so in the presence of water
um this uh
c
s or in this case a c o bond is weak
because of the presence of sulfur and
you'll be hydrolyzed relatively quickly
and then you actually generate the
uh alcohol in no time okay but take note
that
uh remember that in the hydration
of
alkene using
concentrated sulfuric acid the condition
is it must be done in cold condition so
this is actually
the first reagents being added yeah so
in a closed condition you generate this
hydrogen sulfate as a product and then
later on when you pour cold water inside
then this bone will be hydrolyzed and in
the process give you the relevant
alcohols
okay yeah so and that's the end of the
alkenes uh lecture
yep and uh
that will be it for
this current topic and then the next
topic will be on aliens and then do look
out for the next video